Good morning. Today's דף daf 52 נב Nun Bet and
it's a very interesting and fun דף. daf. We discussed two topics.
One is somewhat related. One is a גמרא gemara which has been
used classically in recent periods to be the basis for the idea
of a מחיצה mechitzah in a שול. shul. And then basically the
rest of the דף daf is going to be an extended אגדתא
agadata around the idea of יצר הרע. yeitzer hara. So it'll be
an interesting דף. daf. Let's take a look
seven lines from the bottom of נא עמוד ב. Nun Aleph Amud
Bet. במוצאי יום טוב. Bemotzei Yom Tov. So the משנה mishnah says
the night the first night following יום טוב Yom Tov they would
go into the עזרת נשים Ezrat Nashim and they would fix it
up really well, make a תיקון גדול tikun gadol and then they
would start the partying for the שמחת בית השואבה Simchat Beit Hashoeva
parties which would take place at the night and go into the
next morning where they would draw the water from the well. So
מאי תיקון גדול mai tikun gadol says the גמרא gemara what was
this big fixing up that they did? אמר רבי אלעזר Amar Rabbi
Eleazar says רבי אלעזר Rabbi Eleazar כאותה ששנינו ke'ota sheshaninu like we
taught in a משנה mishnah in
מידות: Middot: חלקה הייתה העזרה חלקה הייתה בראשונה chalaka hayeta ha'azara chalaka
hayeta barishona originally the עזרה azara was smooth was flat the
עזרת נשים Ezrat Nashim והקיפוה גזוסטרא veheikifuha gazustra and they surrounded it
with a גזוסטרא gazustra some type of a protrusion והתקינו שיהו נשים
יושבות מלמעלה ואנשים מלמטה vehitkinu sheyehu nashim yoshvot milmala veanashim milmata and
they made it that women should sit above and men should sit
below so the first balcony in a שול. shul. Now there actually
is an interesting debate here based on רמב"ם Rambam in פירוש המשניות
Peirush Hamishnayot and others exactly what the מלמעלה ומלמטה milmala umilmata is
and what the גזוסטרא gazustra is. Some say a גזוסטרא gazustra because
you think about it if you're talking about women above that suggests
the idea of a balcony but it's contrasting it to the fact
that it had to be smooth and flat. Well making a balcony
doesn't exactly make a place the floor not flat
so I mean I guess you have you could have poles supporting
the balcony. So some say that what we're talking about here is
protrusions. רש"י Rashi says it means that the walls were flat or
smooth and then they made protrusions from the wall to support a
balcony which would be supported by the protrusion. Others say that it
actually means that they would have it would be less of a
balcony and more really the two types of מחיצה mechitzah you know
that we use nowadays. More there would be some type of a
posts behind which the women would stand but maybe like a raised
platform on which the women would stand but it would be a
raised platform on the floor. So are we basically sort of saying
if here's your floor of your עזרה azara are we basically saying
that they would and here's your wall are we basically saying that
they would make like protrusions from the walls and make you know
sort of like things like this so you can stand here on
the balcony? Or are we saying that you would make
actually platforms maybe you know and like stand on the platforms or
something like that? Why exactly you would need platforms is not clear
if you're standing behind a wall but I guess if you want
to see and you're standing behind something you want to be a
little bit raised. Anyway the simple sense about above and below is
that it was some type of a balcony.
Okay Steinsaltz says it's from a Greek word which means a projection
from the side of the house upon which boards are laid. In
other words a balcony גזוסטרא. gazustra.
Yeah that's what רש"י Rashi says that's the protrusion. There is a
רמב"ם Rambam in פירוש המשניות Peirush Hamishnayot though I believe that it
suggests more something like a like being behind some type of a
barrier. But yes clearly this is the simple sense of this is
a balcony. Okay והתקינו שיהו נשים יושבות מלמעלה ואנשים מלמטה vehitkinu sheyehu
nashim yoshvot milmala veanashim milmata
and the women should be above and the men below. So there
you go so they made a balcony for the women. Now תנו
רבנן Tanu Rabbanan our rabbis taught בראשונה היו נשים מבפנים ואנשים מבחוץ
barishona hayu nashim mibifnim veanashim mibachutz
and here's part of also why it's confusing is because whereas the
previous thing pointed to the idea of a sense of a balcony
this suggests more explicitly the other sense of this of a type
of a what we have in a contemporary context of a division
of men and women well again it depends which שול shul you're
in but anyway the standard type of a מחיצה mechitzah where you
know different sections. The women would be on the inside and the
men on the outside. Now inside and outside what? So רש"י Rashi
says it could mean even outside the עזרת נשים Ezrat Nashim on
the הר הבית Har Habayit which is pretty interesting והיו באים לידי
קלות ראש vehayu baim lidei kalut rosh that would lead to levity
to inappropriate mixing
and you know too much maybe sexual tension in the air or
something. So והתקינו שיהו נשים יושבות מבחוץ ואנשים מבפנים vehitkinu sheyehu nashim
yoshvot mibachutz veanashim mibifnim so they put the women on the outside
the men on the inside no idea why that's supposed to make
things better I guess it's who's coming late and which section you
have to cut through to get to the other section or something
I don't know. ועדיין היו באים לידי קלות ראש ve'adayin hayu baim
lidei kalut rosh and it still led to too much frivolity. התקינו
שיהיו נשים יושבות מלמעלה ואנשים מלמטה. Hiskinu she'yihyu nashim yoshvos mil'ma'ala v'anashim
mil'mata.
So then they said rather than side-by-side, which there's some opportunity of
interaction, I guess as you're crossing over or maybe at the edges,
they had the women totally above and the men below, which completely
prevented that. Okay, so that exactly, so that's sort of what preceded
the above and below. Now, so here they made this whole separation
of the sexes and they would do that before this big party.
So היכי עביד הכי, Heichi avid hachi, how could they do that?
והכתיב, V'hachsiv, does the verse not say, הכל בכתב מיד ה' עלי
השכיל, Hakol bichsav miyad Hashem alai hiskil, everything from the hand of
God, from the written hand of God to me was revealed, and
that is about the construction,
דוד המלך David HaMelech saying it about the construction of the בית
המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. I mean, God was, the prophet נתן Natan was
sort of revealing this to,
through דוד David about how, to דוד to David about how the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash had to be constructed. Now, that's quite fascinating
as a question for a couple of reasons. Number one, that was
בית ראשון. Bayis Rishon. This is בית שני. Bayis Sheini. Number two,
בית שני Bayis Sheini was already significantly different than the בית ראשון.
Bayis Rishon. Number three, this is the עזרת נשים, Ezras Nashim, which
is not technically part of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So anyway,
that's whatever the question is, not exactly clear what the question is,
but let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is. אמר רב, Amar
Rav, so רב Rav said, קרא אשכחו ודרוש. Kra ashkechu v'darash. They
found a פסוק pasuk and they explicated it to justify making this
modification.
What was the פסוק? pasuk? וספדה הארץ משפחות משפחות לבד. V'safda ha'aretz
mishpachos mishpachos levad.
This is a פסוק pasuk in זכריה Zechariah talking about the war
of Armageddon and that there'll be a much, you know, the nations
will surround Israel and there'll be a war and then there'll be
death in the war and the land will eulogize for those that
have died in the war. We'll see in a minute the גמרא's
Gemara going to identify a particular figure that has died in the
war. Every family separately, משפחת בית דוד לבד ונשיהם לבד, Mishpachas Beis
David levad u'nesheihem levad, the family of בית דוד Beis David by
themselves and their wives alone, and then it says משפחת בית נתן
לבד ונשיהם לבד. Mishpachas Beis Natan levad u'nesheihem levad. So first of
all, each family is doing their own eulogizing in separate groups, and
within each family, the men and the women are separate. So you
see, אמרו, amru, they said, look, זה לאו קל וחומר, zeh lav
kal v'chomer, we can make from this a קל וחומר. kal v'chomer.
ומה לעתיד לבוא שעוסקים בהספד, U'ma l'asid lavo she'oskim b'hesped, in the
future time, a, at a time of a funeral, everybody's eulogizing, ואין
יצר הרע שולט בהם, v'ein yeitzer hara sholeit bahem, and they also
don't have the evil inclination, the evil inclination doesn't have dominion over
them. So why, what does that mean? So it could just be
that's an explication of עוסקים בהספד, oskim b'hesped, that if you're busy
mourning and at the aftermath of a great tragedy, it's not usually
a time when there's a lot of sexual desire, you know, everybody's
in a very different type of mood. But the other thing that
רש"י Rashi also adds here, getting to what the גמרא's Gemara going
to say in a minute, is if this is a messianic vision,
at that time there will no longer be a יצר הרע. yeitzer
hara. So like, it's not just at that moment of the הספד,
hesped, but at that time in history, the יצר הרע yeitzer hara
will have been negated. And even so, אמרה תורה אנשים לבד ונשים
לבד, amra Torah anashim levad v'nashim levad, that men and women have
to be separate. עכשיו, Achshav, nowadays, שעוסקים בשמחה, she'oskim b'simcha, number one,
it's all this joy and frivolity, and that usually can lead to
it, to a heightening, like you know, to enticing sexual desire and
so on and it leads you to be frivolous and get carried
away, ויצר הרע שולט בהם, v'yeitzer hara sholeit bahem, again that could
be just explicating the reality of עוסקים בשמחה oskim b'simcha or again,
as what רש"י Rashi says, it's a period of history in which
there's a reality of a יצר הרע. yeitzer hara. על אחת כמה
וכמה, Al achas kama v'kama, how much more so do we need
to keep the men and the women separate? So this is why
they felt they were justified in making some modification. Again, not even
clear, it sounds like it was, anyway again, another reason why this
wasn't even so much of a question is that it sounds like
it was a temporary modification, right? It sounds like if they had
to do it every year, then obviously they didn't keep it from
year to year. So but whatever it was, whether they needed it
to justify actually making a change or whether it was the question
about where did they get the idea in the first place that
they should keep the men and the women separate, it quotes this
idea from this mourning period לעתיד לבוא. l'asid lavo. Now here's the
interesting thing, okay? And I'm not going to, this is not a
שיעור shiur on מחיצה, mechitzah, so I'm not going to go into
detail about this. But there is no statement anywhere in the גמרא
Gemara that you need a מחיצה mechitzah between men and women during
דאוונינג. davening. There's no statement that men and women were mixed during
דאוונינג. davening. There's no statement that men and women were separate during
דאוונינג. davening. There's no statement anyway one way or the other, which
could mean, you know, there was an established practice and it didn't
need to be commented on. But anyway, but it's quite interesting that
there is not an explicit statement. So it clearly is recorded historically
as practice from the time of the גאונים Geonim on. We don't
have any evidence earlier what exactly the practice was.
The explicit historical evidence is from the time of the גאונים Geonim
where they were sitting men and women separate. It didn't need to
be justified, it was just taken for granted. It became needed to
be justified in the more modern period starting with the חתם סופר.
Chasam Sofer. This was even before the reformers challenged, actually, early reformers
in. In Europe did not have mixed seating. Mixed seating, I believe,
somebody could correct me, began in America. I think Albany. In Albany.
Yeah. Anyway, but the חתם סופר Chatam Sofer did not need to
defend against the reformers, but anyway, it was a time where there
was actually a fascinating תשובה teshuva where the Czar was visiting Saint
Petersburg, I think, and they wanted to welcome him in the main
synagogue in Saint Petersburg and they wanted to have a mixed choir
singing for him and they asked the חתם סופר Chatam Sofer whether
they were allowed to. So that led to a whole discussion about
קול באישה ערווה kol b'isha erva but also a discussion of keeping
men and women separate. So when it first became this issue of
the need to explicate the importance of keeping men and women separate
in the דאוונינג, davening, this גמרא Gemara became one of the primary
sources which was used to explain why men and women have to
be kept separate during דאוונינג, davening, because it speaks about, look, they
kept men and women separate during the שמחת בית השואבה. Simchat Beit
Hashoeva. Now the problem with, and it's interesting again also because it
has the two models of how they were kept separate: with a
balcony or with separate in separate sections. The only problem is that
this גמרא Gemara is either way too narrow or way too broad.
It's too narrow because you could say, look, fine, they kept them
separate in the middle of having a huge party and frivolity and
whatever. Okay, fine, that doesn't mean when you're דאוונינג. davening. So fine,
but look, the גמרא Gemara says it's a קל וחומר kal v'chomer
from the case about eulogizing when there's no frivolity and everything is
super serious and even there you have to keep them separate. But
then it becomes too broad, then you would have to keep men
and women separate at all times. So exactly how from this גמרא
Gemara you get to this middle position that you keep men and
women separate during
דאוונינג, davening, but not just at times of frivolity and not at
all times is a little bit unclear. But this גמרא Gemara is
for many a major
basis or textual support for the idea of a מחיצה mechitza during
דאוונינג davening and the issue about whether it's in a balcony or
whether it's side-by-side and so on is also a question about what
the purpose of that separation is. If a balcony suffices, then the
balcony is what they did in the end, then the purpose of
separation has to do with intermingling, not with seeing one another, because
you can see one another pretty well from a balcony. If the
issue is about if it's more about the sort of side-by-side separation
or a wall type of a separation, which some want to say
is what was being referred to, then maybe there's an issue of
seeing one another as opposed to the intermingling. The simple sense of
this גמרא Gemara I would say much more underscores the aspect of
the intermingling and that also is very relevant for questions about the
nature if you use this גמרא Gemara as your source for the
nature of מחיצה. mechitza. Yes, Yosef Baber.
What?
Of course it was a balcony?
How do you know?
The חתם סופר Chatam Sofer in Europe.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, in Europe. Yeah, yeah, yeah, right. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara continues. So that is anyway, yes,
but it leads to קלות ראש.
kalut rosh.
From this, well, I mean, all right, from this גמרא Gemara you
don't, but of course בוא לידי קלות ראש bo lidei kalut rosh
as a concern because the men and the women were mixing and
it wouldn't be a concern when they weren't mixing. They were having
just as much torch juggling and drinking and dancing without, so if
that's not קלות ראש, kalut rosh, but once you get some mixing
it is קלות ראש. kalut rosh. I mean, seems like it has
something to do with that. Anyway, you'd have to look at other
סוגיות, sugyot, but it seems that it is related. Okay, so now
we're going to take a look, now it's also worth noting the
association of יצר הרע yeitzer hara before it was קלות ראש, kalut
rosh, but יצר הרע yeitzer hara with this issue of this intermingling
of men and women. And how much is יצר הרע yeitzer hara
identified with sexual desire, or is it just more generally? I was
just reading an article last night, I mean, this גמרא Gemara gave
me the reason to read an article that I had seen before
but hadn't maybe
had a chance to read before, which is about the development of
the concept of יצר הרע yeitzer hara from the Tannaic through the
Amoraic period. You know, we tend to think about, if you ask
what is sort of the rabbinic understanding of יצר הרע, yeitzer hara,
we tend to think it's like often internalized, you know, we think
about יצר הרע yeitzer hara in contrast to יצר הטוב. yeitzer hatov.
It's sort of your struggle with your more
appetitive desires as opposed to your id as opposed to your
super-ego, your better side, your worse side, so we internalize it. And
we often think very much that it often is associated maybe primarily
or largely with sexual desire.
So those are like some classic characteristics that we have of יצר
הרע. yeitzer hara. So you know, but this article basically said that
actually the earlier understandings of it didn't have either of those, sort
of an external force, you know, if we just even look at
the phrase יצר הרע שולט בהם. yeitzer hara sholet bahem. So is
it שולט sholet an internal שולט sholet or שולט sholet like this
demonic force that has power over us, right? Is it more a
sense of like a demonic power of evil that entices us but
it's externalized? And maybe it's not specifically about appetitive desire. can be
channeled for good, you know, sort of the drive, you know, sort
of, you know, all these types of drives which can be, you
know, which can also be productive, maybe it's just this sense of
an enticement to do evil, like an external demonic power that is
enticing us to sin, and it's not specific about sex, and it's
not about an appetitive drive. So, you know, and how it sort
of transitions from that externalized type of a thing to this internalized,
you know, struggle with also desires which also can be seen as
powerful desires that can be channeled for better. So anyway, it's interesting
here as well that let's as we read this סוגיא, sugya, because
a lot of this, we're going to now discuss the rest of
the דף, daf, discussing יצר הרע, yetzer hara, and a lot of
this also there's an interesting parallel in בראשית רבה Bereshit Rabbah by
the פסוק pasuk of, you know, where God says to קין, Kayin,
he says, לפתח חטאת רבץ, lappetach chatat roveitz, ואתה תמשול בו, ve-atah
timshol bo, that that which is seen as referring like the יצר
הרע yetzer hara as external and trying to entice you to גיהנום,
Gehennom, but you can have control over him, and this is really
again, this sort of model of this other idea of this externalized
idea. So let's sort of take a look and see how that
develops, but here certainly it is, if
not, it is first being introduced to us in the context of
sexual desire. Yes, Charlie.
Yeah, the משנה Mishnah only says תיקון גדול tikkun gadol and it's
תוספתא Tosefta that gives the details. If it were that important, why
didn't רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi include it in the משנה?
Mishnah?
That important for what? For this whole—I'm not discussing—what, the contemporary argument
for מחיצה? mechitzah? Okay, but it's a משנה Mishnah in מדות. Middot.
What do you mean—what do you mean it's that important? It would
just be a historical point. It's only important, you mean, if you
decide that you're going to use this as your basis for your
understanding. Fine. Yeah.
Anyway, it is a משנה Mishnah in מדות. Middot. Yes.
There was a science fiction film called Forbidden Planet. Yes. And it
had the concept that the actually external physical reality, but it was
created by the mind. Aha.
That project—they
were under the—this culture, the civilization, or whatever it was, it was
the mind created it and created an external force that then was
the negative force. Interesting.
Interesting. Nice way of bringing those together. Right. Okay. So let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
Now, האי הספידא מאי עבידתיה? a-hai speda mai avidite? What was the
point of this eulogy? פליגי בה רבי דוסא ורבנן. pleigi ba Rabbi
Dosa ve-Rabbanan. So it's a debate of רבי דוסא Rabbi Dosa and
the Rabbis. חד אמר משיח בן יוסף שנהרג. chad amar mashiach ben
Yosef sheneharg. It's the משיח Mashiach the son of יוסף. Yosef. Now
some people have never heard of משיח בן יוסף. Mashiach ben Yosef.
It's not really in anywhere explicit, but it is a Rabbinic understanding
that, you know, in the vision of Armageddon in זכריה, Zekharia,
it speaks about obviously this whole war against Israel and the, and
there's a lot of death and whatever, and finally משיח Mashiach comes.
So the Rabbis understand that part of who will lead them into
war is משיח בן יוסף. Mashiach ben Yosef. Where do they get
this idea? Because the פסוק pasuk says, והיה בית יוסף אש ובית
יוסף אש—what vehayah beit Yosef eish u-veit Yosef eish is it?—ובית יעקב
להבה והיה עשו לקש. u-veit Yaakov lehavah vehayah Eisav lekash. So a
vision about how the destroying of the enemies of עשו Eisav or
whatever is by comparing the house of יוסף Yosef to a fire,
that the original person, sort of leader that will lead the war
against the enemies will be from the house of יוסף, Yosef, will
be משיח בן יוסף. Mashiach ben Yosef. And he'll die in the
war, and then will arrive משיח בן דוד Mashiach ben David who
will be the ultimate משיח. Mashiach. So it says, so that's who
they're mourning, משיח בן יוסף שנהרג. Mashiach ben Yosef sheneharg. וחד אמר
על יצר הרע שנהרג. ve-chad amar al yetzer hara sheneharg. No,
the יצר הרע yetzer hara will be killed because then it'll be
the Messianic time. בשלמא למאן דאמר משיח בן יוסף שנהרג, bishlama le-man
d'amar mashiach ben Yosef sheneharg, so it's good if you say it
was משיח—meaning Mashiach as an explanation of the verse, it was משיח
בן יוסף Mashiach ben Yosef who was murdered. היינו דכתיב והביטו אלי
את אשר דקרו, hayinu d'chtiv vehibitu elai et asher dakaru,
they will look towards me that which way had been like sort
of pierced through, the person who had been murdered. וספדו עליו כמספד
על היחיד, ve-safdu alav k'misped al ha-yachid, and they will mourn over
him like the mourning over a like of a single, your only
child. אלא—so ella it's a human being who was killed, and that's—this
is referring to this period after this in this war of Armageddon.
אלא למאן דאמר על יצר הרע שנהרג, ella le-man d'amar al yetzer
hara sheneharg, but if it was the יצר הרע, yetzer hara, האי
הספידא בעי למיעבד? hai speda ba'ei le-me'ebad?
What? You're going to do a eulogy? שמחה בעי למיעבד! simcha ba'ei
le-me'ebad! You should be doing a rejoicing! So it's funny, because you
assume that it was going to have a problem with the verse.
Forget the verse. The verse could be talking about whoever it's talking
about, but why are you eulogizing? You should be having a party.
אמאי בכו? amai bachu? Why did they—why did they cry? כדדרש רבי
יהודה, kede-darash Rabbi Yehuda, as רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda explains. לעתיד לבוא,
le-atid lavo, in the future time, where am I? מביא הקדוש ברוך
הוא ליצר הרע, mevi ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu le-yetzer hara,
God will bring the יצר הרע, yetzer hara, ושוחטו בפני הצדיקים, ve-shochato
bifnei ha-tzaddikim, and slaughter it in front of the righteous, ובפני הרשעים,
u-vifnei ha-resha'im, and in front of the and in front of the
evil people. צדיקים נדמה להם כהר גבוה tzadikim nidmeh lahem ke'har gavoha
for the righteous it looks like this huge mountain ורשעים נדמה להם
כחוט השערה ve'reshaim nidmeh lahem ke'chut hasa'arah and for the wicked it
looks like a one thread of hair. הללו בוכים והללו בוכים, halalu
bochim ve'halalu bochim, these go and cry and these go and cry.
צדיקים בוכים ואומרים, tzadikim bochim ve'omrim,
the righteous go cry and say היך יכולנו לכבוש הר גבוה כזה,
heich yacholnu lichbosh har gavoha kaze, how could we, how did we
ever have the ability to conquer this huge mountain? ורשעים בוכים ואומרים,
u'reshaim bochim ve'omrim, and the wicked go and cry and they say
היך לא יכולנו לכבוש את חוט השערה הזה, heich lo yacholnu lichbosh
es chut hasa'arah haze, how were we not able to overcome this
tiny little thread? ואף הקדוש ברוך הוא תמה עמהם ve'af hakadosh baruch
hu tameh imahem and even God is astounded with them שנאמר she'ne'emar
כה אמר השם צבאות, ko amar Hashem Tzevaos, so says the Lord
of hosts כי יפלא בעיני שארית העם הזה בימים ההם, ki yipaleh
be'einei she'eris ha'am haze bayamim haheim, if it will be astounding in
the eyes of this people in those days גם בעיני יפלא, gam
be'einai yipaleh, even in My eyes it'll be astounding. Now I don't
know what this means. First of all I will tell you a
brilliant insight that the מהרשא Maharsha has about the mountain and the
hair. He says that הר שעיר, Har Seir, so he says because
עשו Eisav is often you know sort of seen as not just
the enemies of the Jews whatever but it represents the evil forces
against the Jews the יצר הרע, yetzer hara, so הר שעיר Har
Seir is sort of the paradigm enemy, so it could be you
know the human enemy and it could be the יצר הרע. yetzer
hara. So therefore עשו Eisav lives on הר שעיר, Har Seir, so
that's the הר har the mountain and the שער sear the hair.
So that was very cute. But what is this idea that first
of all the righteous are crying? Why are they crying? There's no
יצר הרע. yetzer hara. So רשי Rashi says they're crying because they're
crying over how difficult they're remembering how hard it was in the
course of their lives to struggle with the יצר הרע. yetzer hara.
So they're crying over all of their past struggles. The מהרשא Maharsha
says, first he says the פשט pshat sounds like they're crying out
of joy. Okay but he says but that doesn't work, then you're
not having a הספד. hesped. So he says so maybe, he says,
they're crying because they're now losing the opportunity to have this religious
struggle in order to gain all the reward that they were gaining.
Now that's you know now it's easy for everybody. We were you
know we were living up to the struggle. Anyway it's hard to
understand exactly why the righteous are struggling. What's also hard to understand
is why it looks to the righteous like a mountain and like
the wicked like a hair, right? You know because it sounds like
that, right, it should be the other way around. And it sounds
like that this is like you know what they say like the
scales fall from their eyes like the truth is revealed. So you
sort of get it you get the idea that somebody who's wicked
and feels like you know they're always it's so hard for them
to live up to their you know to fight their temptation, it's
so hard for them to do the right thing that you know
that in a way they're like fooling themselves, that really if they
could have a little willpower you know then they could start making
things better and they could start acting in the right way and
once if the scales fell from their eyes they would realize it's
not as hard as they think it is, you know, it just
needs a little change of direction a little willpower, and so that
I could you can see that like it becomes revealed to them
that it was not as difficult as they thought it was. It
was like a hair wasn't a mountain. But what does the opposite
mean for the for the צדיקים? tzadikim? If you by that analogy
it means that for the צדיקים tzadikim it seems like it was
very easy but it was really this huge mountain. So I suppose
what that would mean is that if you're really like working on
yourself and you're constantly working to be better and so on, you
know, a lot of things, you know, that normally would be it's
like when you start you know you know it's like if you're
an exerciser, right? So and you start getting better and better like
you know I know a lot of people that they went from
nothing to running a marathon. Like they say that's completely impossible. היך
יכולנו לכבוש הר גבוה כזה, heich yacholnu lichbosh har gavoha kaze, I
could never imagine that, right? But you know you slowly train and
you make a lot of incremental you know improvements bit by bit
and next thing you know you're doing it and it's not a
challenge because you know you're not going from here to here every
time, you're just taking a little step. But after a while you
know but then you realize oh my God how the heck did
I do that? How was I able to run a marathon? A
year ago I couldn't run a marathon. But when you're in the
middle of it like if you're on the right path and you're
exercising the muscles correctly you know it's not such a challenge. So
I think that that's like I think that's what it's saying that
you know the scales fall from their eyes and maybe for the
צדיקים tzadikim maybe if they didn't experience it like a הר har
but that's cause they were you know cause if you experience it
like a הר har then you're just going to give up hope.
But if you sort of focus on just getting a little bit
better then when you look back and you realize oh my God
how did I how did I accomplish that? All right again why
exactly you're crying I don't know but okay. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. Okay
and then God is also astounded like presumably astounded at the רשעים,
reshaim, like I don't get it guys how could you how could
you not have done it? It was not as hard as you
made it seem like and how do you you know how'd you
how'd you stray so far? Or maybe He's astounded at the צדיקים
tzadikim that they managed to accomplish that much. Okay אמר רב
אסי Amar Rav Assi יצר הרע בתחילה דומה לחוט של בוכיא. yetzer
hara batchila domeh le'chut shel buchyah. The יצר הרע yetzer hara *Yetzer
hara* originally is like a spider web. It's not even such a
big יצר הרע yetzer hara *Yetzer hara*. This gets back to the
חוט השערה *chut hase'arah*. You know, tiny little temptations, ובסוף דומה כאבותות
העגלה *u'basof domeh ka'avotot ha'agala*. And by the end, it's like the
cords used to drag to to pull a wagon, like really thick
cords. Okay, meaning if you, you know, those little the little temptations,
if you don't give into them, you know, then you're free from
them, but once you start giving into one, it's then you start
then you do the next thing and the next thing, and the
next thing you know, you're deep into a habit of going down
the wrong path, of doing the right the wrong things, you know,
and it's very, very hard to break away from those addictions and
those habits. So, שנאמר Shene'emar *she'ne'emar*, הוי מושכי העוון בחבלי השווא *hoy
moshchei he'avon bechavlei hashava*, woe to those who draw the sin upon
them with ropes of nothingness. So that's like a spider with thread,
a spider web. וכאבותות העגלה חטאה *u'ka'avotot ha'agala chata'ah*, and like the
cords of the wagon, they'll bring upon them sin. So it begins
from nothing and then look how thick it becomes and impossible to
break free of. תנו רבנן Tanu rabanan, *Tanu rabanan*, משיח בן דוד
Mashiach ben David, שעתיד להתגלות במהרה בימינו *Mashiach ben David she'atid lehitgalot
bimheira beyameinu*. So every fast, I mean, no, but very powerful גמראs
Gemara. *Gemaras* we just read about sort of the psychological realities of,
you know, of of addiction and behavior and habit and all of
those. So תנו רבנן *Tanu rabanan*, our rabbis taught, משיח בן יוסף
*Mashiach ben Yosef* wait wait wait... משיח בן דוד Mashiach ben David,
שעתיד להתגלות במהרה בימינו *Mashiach ben David she'atid lehitgalot bimheira beyameinu*, משיח
בן דוד David, *Mashiach ben David* you normally just call משיח *Mashiach*,
but again because here we're in a discussion of משיח בן דוד
Dovid, *Mashiach ben David* and משיח בן יוסף *Mashiach ben Yosef*. So
משיח בן דוד Dovid *Mashiach ben David* that will eventually reveal be
be revealed quickly in our days, אומר לו הקדוש ברוך הוא *omer
lo Hakadosh Baruch Hu*, God says to him at this in the
future time, שאל ממני דבר ואתן לך *she'al mimeni davar ve'eten lach*,
ask of me anything and I'll give it to you, שנאמר Shene'emar
*she'ne'emar*, and this is a פסוק pasuk *pasuk* in the beginning of
תהילים *Tehillim* פרק ב' *Perek Bet*, and if you look in the
context, it is about משיח *Mashiach*. It says the following. It says
אספרה אל חוק *asapra el chok*, I will talk tell talk about
the decree, אני היום ילדתיך *ani hayom yeladeticha*, I today have given
birth to you, meaning today I have revealed that that you are
the משיח *Mashiach*. שאל ממני ואתנה גויים נחלתך *she'al mimeni ve'etnah goyim
nachalatecha*, ask from me anything and I'll give the nations as your
inheritance. וכיוון שראה משיח בן יוסף שנהרג *vekeivan sherah Mashiach ben Yosef
she'neherag*, but then when משיח בן דוד *Mashiach ben David* sees that
משיח בן יוסף *Mashiach ben Yosef* has been killed in war, אמר
לפניו *amar lefanav*, he says to God, ריבונו של עולם *Ribono shel
Olam*, Master of the Universe, איני מבקש ממך אלא חיים *eini mevakesh
mimcha ela chayim*, I don't want anything, I don't want to conquer
all the nations, all I want is life. Maybe he means I
want to live life for myself, I don't want to die like
משיח בן יוסף *Mashiach ben Yosef*, maybe he means life for the
world, that there will never be death anymore, תחיית המתים *t'chiyat hameitim*,
but he sees all of the death and rather than wanting more
of like the this worldly thing of conquering the nations, he wants
a different type of a reality, he wants life. אומר לו *Omer
lo*, so God says to him, חיים *chayim*, life? עד שלא אמרת
כבר התנבא עליך דוד אביך *ad she'lo amarta kvar hitnabei alecha David
avicha*, before you ask for it, דוד *David* had already prophesied that
you would be given life, שנאמר Shene'emar *she'ne'emar*, חיים שאל ממך נתת
לו *chayim sha'al mimcha natata lo*, he has asked from you life,
you have given it to him. This is a מזמור *mizmor* that
is about all the ways in which God has given amazing things
to the king and presumably this is being read as the king
משיח *Mashiach*. Okay, so that was just going back to the משיח
*Mashiach* theme, but but then again about sort of a switching about
לעתיד לבוא *le'atid lavo*. Now we hear that לעתיד לבוא *le'atid lavo*
there won't be a יצר הרע Yetzer hara *yetzer hara* and there
also won't be death. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* isn't going to
be focusing on לעתיד לבוא *le'atid lavo*, that's other גמראs Gemara *Gemaras*.
This גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to go back to be focusing
on יצר הרע yetzer hara. *yetzer hara*. דרש רב אבירא ואיתימא רבי
יהושע בן לוי *Darash Rav Avira ve'iteima Rabi Yehoshua ben Levi*, שבעה
שמות *shiva shemot*, seven names יש לו ליצר הרע *yesh lo l'yetzer
hara*, the יצר הרע yetzer hara *yetzer hara* has seven names. הקדוש
ברוך הוא קראו רע *Hakadosh Baruch Hu kera'o ra*, God called it
evil, שנאמר Shene'emar, *she'ne'emar*, כי יצר yetzer. לב האדם רע מנעוריו *ki
yetzer lev ha'adam ra mine'urav*. משה קראו ערל *Moshe kera'o arel*, uncircumcised,
שנאמר Shene'emar, *she'ne'emar*, ומלתם את ערלת לבבכם *umaltem et orlat levavchem*, you
should you should circumcise the the foreskin of your heart. דוד קראו
טמא *David kera'o tamei*, דוד *David* called it impure, שנאמר Shene'emar, *she'ne'emar*,
לב טהור ברא לי אלוהים *lev tahor b'ra li Elohim*, God made
for me a pure heart, מכלל דאיכא טמא *miklal de'ika tamei*, that
means there's such a thing as an impure heart. שלמה קראו שונא
*Shlomo kera'o sonei*, שלמה *Shlomo* called it a hater or an enemy,
whatever, a hated one, שנאמר Shene'emar, *she'ne'emar*, אם רעב שונאך *im ra'ev
sone'acha*, if the one you hate is hungry, האכילהו לחם *he'achilehu lechem*,
feed him bread, ואם צמא השקהו מים *ve'im tzamei hashkehu mayim*, and
if he's thirsty give him water, כי גחלים אתה חותה על ראשו
*ki gechalim ata choteh al rosho*, because you're really doing is you're
dumping coals on his head, so be nice to your enemy and
it'll get them, it'll, you know, it'll it'll
get under their skin, it'll it'll be worse for them than being
mean to them. Okay, וה' ישלם לך *v'Hashem yeshalem lach*, and God
will pay you back. אל תקרי ישלם לך אלא ישלימנו לך *Al
tikrei yeshalem lach ela yashlimenu lach*, do not read will pay you
back, but will have you make peace with it. So רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* says what this means is it's it's alluding to so anyway,
so it's being read as not literally your enemies but the יצר
הרע yetzer hara *yetzer hara*. And what does it mean give him
bread and give him water? And רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says it means
תורה Torah. *Torah*. So if your יצר הרע yetzer hara is hungry
and you have a desire to sin and it wants to be
fed with sin, instead of feeding it with sin, feed it with
תורה. Torah And then you'll make peace with it and you'll be
able to redirect your יצר. yeitzer, Okay,
ישעיהו קראו מכשול. Yeshayahu karo michshol. ישעיהו Yeshayahu called it a stumbling
block. שנאמר Shene'emar, סולו סולו פנו דרך solo solo panu derech clear
out clear out the way הרימו מכשול מדרך עמי harimu michshol miderech
ami remove the stumbling block from the way of my people.
יחזקאל קראו אבן. Yechezkel karo even. יחזקאל Yechezkel called it a stone.
שנאמר shene'emar, והסירותי את לב האבן מבשרכם vahasiroti et lev ha'even mivsarchem
I will remove the stone of heart the the from your from
your flesh ונתתי לכם לב בשר. venatati lachem lev basar. יואל קראו
צפוני. Yoel karo tzfoni. יואל Yoel called it the either northern one
or the hidden one. שנאמר ואת הצפוני ארחיק מעליכם ve'et hatzfoni archik
me'aleichem I will distance the צפוני tzfoni from you. It's interesting to
note based on the point I made before how some of these
images are external and some are internal. I don't know if you
picked that up, right the uncircumcised heart, the stone heart, the pure
heart, that's all very internal, right as opposed to the stumbling block,
the enemy, the impure you know the what was the first one,
the evil, you know there's a very almost shift between external and
internal here. Okay. תנו רבנן, a rabbi taught, ואת הצפוני ארחיק מעליכם,
ve'et hatzfoni archik me'aleichem, זה יצר הרע, ze yetzer hara, this is
the evil inclination, שצפון ועומד בלבו של אדם shetzafun ve'omed belibo shel
adam
that it is hidden and standing in the heart of a man
so there you get it's internalized. והדחתיו אל ארץ ציה ושממה vehidachtiv
el eretz tziya ushemama I will push it away to a barren
and desolate land, למקום שאין בני אדם מצויים להתגרות בהן limkom she'ein
bnei adam metzuyim lehitgarot bahen to a place where there's no people
so it will not not be able to sort of entice other
people, you know make trouble with other people, so there you got
talk about it being externalized. It's sort of like I'll take it
out from being inside of you and cast it away from people.
So it's a lot of this mix here of this internal external.
סופו. Sofo.
שנתן עיניו במקדש שאין אחרים להתגרות בהם. shenatan einav bemikdash she'ein acherim
lehitgarot bahem. את פניו אל הים הקדמוני. et panav el hayam hakadmoni.
So this is again quoting sections of the פסוק pasuk and then
as it were interpreting it. So I will have it its face
the the the
eastern sea. שנתן Shenatan so this is reading ים yam as the
בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash because everybody gathered like everyone you know it's
like a god collects all the waters, everybody gathers to the בית
המקדש Beit Hamikdash and קדמון kadmon meaning the first בית המקדש. Beit
Hamikdash. שנתן עיניו במקדש ראשון shenatan einav bemikdash rishon that it looked
that the יצר הרע yetzer hara, put its eyes towards the first
בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash והחריבו vehecherivo and caused it to be destroyed
or destroyed it והרג תלמידי חכמים שבו veharag talmidei chachamim shebo and
killed all of the
sages or whatever תורה Torah scholars among in them. וסופו אל הים
האחרון vesofo el hayam ha'acharon its end I will place towards the
western sea, what does that mean? שנתן עיניו במקדש שני shenatan einav
bemikdash sheni that it also gave its eyes towards the second בית
המקדש Beit Hamikdash והחריבו vehecherivo and destroyed it והרג תלמידי חכמים שבו.
veharag talmidei chachamim shebo. Okay. ועלה באשו ותעל צחנתו ve'ala va'asho vata'al
tzachanato and its stench will raise go up and its stench
will go up. שמניח אומות העולם ומתגרה בשונאיהם של ישראל shemaniach umot
ha'olam umitgare beson'eihem shel Yisrael because it abandons the other nations and
it focuses its energies on the Jewish people, what a disgusting thing
to do. כי הגדיל לעשות ki higdil la'asot because it is acts
so greatly because it has done largely, hugely. אמר אביי Amar Abaye
בתלמידי חכמים יותר מכולם betalmidei chachamim yoter mikulam it basically it entices
the תורה Torah. sages. We mentioned תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim twice before
by destroying the בתי המקדש batei hamikdash and the תלמידי חכמים talmidei
chachamim which is an interesting putting together. What's this point of תלמידי
חכמים talmidei chachamim together with בית המקדש? Beit Hamikdash? Anyway and אביי
Abaye says and the יצר הרע yetzer hara. focuses on the תלמידי
חכמים talmidei chachamim more than anyone else. Okay. What does it mean?
כי הא דאביי Ki ha d'Abaye like אביי Abaye שמעיה לההוא גברא
shamei'lei le'hahu gavra he heard a person דקאמר לההיא איתתא de'ka'amar le'hahi
itata so this is a very famous גמרא. He heard a person
דקאמר לההיא איתתא de'ka'amar le'hahi itata he said to a woman נקדים
וניזיל באורחא nakdim venizil be'orcha let's get up early and go take
a long walk together on the way. אמר אזיל אפשינהו מאיסורא. Amar
azil afashinhu me'isura. He said I'm going to travel along with them
I'm going to so the high you know so to sneak behind
them and make sure that it doesn't that I can separate them
from sin. It sounds to me like it's a little assignation who
knows what they're what they're planning on doing I'm I'll make sure
that I'll prevent them. אזל בתרייהו
תלתא פרסי. Azal batreihu tlata parsi. He followed them for three פרסאות
parsaot which is whatever that is what that's a four מיל mil
a מיל mil is a kilometer like 12 kilometers what is that
like eight miles or something. Okay so באגמא be'agma in a אגמא
agma is like a a what is it like a not a
swamp but like a field a yeah. Sometime marsh. Marsh. Okay. כי
הוו פרשי מהדדי Ki havu parshi mehadei then they came to crossroads
and they had to go their separate ways. שמעינהו דקא אמרי Shameinhu
de'ka amri he heard them say one to another אורחא רחיקא orcha
rachika it was a very long journey וצוותא בסומא vetzavta basuma and
how and how pleasing was the company. Thank you so much you
made it such an easy trip it was so nice to be
able to walk and to talk to somebody while we were going
on our journey. So and they didn't do anything wrong. So אמר
אביי Amar Abaye so אביי Abaye said. if that was the person
who was hated to me, which means himself, but he's speaking euphemistically
like שונאיהם של ישראל, Sonayhem shel Yisrael, לא הוי מצי לאוקמי נפשיה,
Lo havay matzi l'okmi nafshay, I would not have been able to
withstand the temptation. So he says he couldn't believe that this person
was able these people were able to do it and he imagined
himself in that situation, he could not have withstood the temptation. So
אזל תלא נפשיה בעיבורא דדשא, Azal tala nafshay b'ibura d'dasha, he grew
very despondent. You know, he thought that he was at this very
high religious level and he realized that you know that that's how
you know how he would have been tempted. So one also has
to wonder about the whole idea about sneaking behind them or whatever,
seems a little bit, you know, as well sort of indicating a
certain desire there. So anyway, he went and he and he leaned
against the beam of a door. ומצטער, U'mitztayer, and he was in
anguish. אתא ההוא סבא, Ata hahu saba, a certain elder came, תנא
ליה, Tana lay, כל הגדול מחבירו יצרו גדול הימנו, Kol hagadol m'chavero
yitzro gadol himenu, the greater a person is, the greater his יצר
הרע yetzer hara is. Okay, so this is a very famous line
כל הגדול מחבירו יצרו גדול הימנו Kol hagadol m'chavero yitzro gadol himenu
and exactly what it's trying to say. You know,
and going back to
the point I raised before about externalizing or internalizing, you know, you
could read it both ways. You know, look, there's a famous מדרש
Midrash that רש״י Rashi quotes right at the beginning of וירא אלהים
את כל אשר עשה והנה טוב מאוד, Vayar Elohim et kol asher
asa v'hineh tov me'od, טוב מאוד זו יצר הרע. Tov me'od zu
yetzer hara. So what does it mean טוב מאוד זו יצר הרע?
Tov me'od zu yetzer hara? I mean why is that טוב מאוד?
tov me'od? So the רמב״ן Ramban has one very interesting reading which
means טוב מאוד tov me'od means it's largely good, mostly good. The
part that isn't good is the יצר הרע. yetzer hara? But it
seems like the מדרש Midrash is trying to say something else, right,
because it says זו יצר הרע שאלמלי יצר הרע לא בנה אדם
בית ולא נשא אדם אשה. Zu yetzer hara she'ilmalei yetzer hara lo
bana adam bayis v'lo nasa adam isha. Right, if the יצר הרע
yetzer hara is this drive in you, so the
drive can be channeled, like you know, to be acquisitive, to whatever,
but it can be channeled to be good things, like okay, so
you'll build a huge שול shul and you'll put your name on
it, but at least you built a huge שול, shul, you have
ambition, but you have that ambition translated into doing good for the
world, right? Or you know, there's sexual desire, but sexual desire can
be fulfilled in the context of a family and raising kids and
connecting to another person. So these drives can be channeled and can
be very good and can make the world a much better place.
So read that way, where we're again sort of talking about
יצר הרע yetzer hara as these internal drives, כל הגדול מחבירו יצרו
גדול הימנו Kol hagadol m'chavero yitzro gadol himenu is exactly true. Some
of the greatest people in the world, what pushes them to be
great is that they have very strong drives, right? So it doesn't
necessarily mean the biggest תלמיד חכם יצרו גדול הימנו, Talmid chacham yitzro
gadol himenu, but that somebody you know very, very driven. People could
be driven and do very bad things, people could be driven and
do very good things. Sometimes the people that are great public people
also you know, have you find out about their private lives and
their you know their יצר הרע yetzer hara is sort of you
know what like you know finding its outlet in other ways there
too, right? But you know, but it could speak about the point
of what it means about having these sort of powerful drives and
the way they could lead. You know, the problem with that, although
obviously I think there's you know, there's obviously an enormous amount of
truth to that, is that it could also be used as a
license. Like you know, oh, you know, see I'm such a great
person, I've got such a strong יצר הרע, yetzer hara so I
could be excused therefore if I'm going to go ahead and do
these various types of things because I'm just I've just got such
a big יצר הרע. yetzer hara So anyway, that's a real big
problem. But I think as a psychological point about what it means
to be have these very powerful drives and the way they could
lead. You know, the other possibility of the גמרא here, seeing it
not as internal but
externalized, like יצר הרע yeitzer hara, leaves the אומות העולם umot ha'olam
and focuses on ישראל. Yisrael. What does that mean? It means the
other nations don't have powerful drives to do good or evil or
whatever, only ישראל Yisrael has the יצר הרע? yeitzer hara So that's
really to externalize it and externalize like also the יצר הרע yeitzer
hara destroyed the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. You know, what does that
mean, the יצר הרע yeitzer hara destroyed the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash?
Because it led us to sin and our sin? That does sound
like יצר הרע yeitzer hara being seen much more here as like
a force of bad in the world. Okay. And as such, if
read that way, it means it means something very different. It means
that a metaphysical level like you know, like
the יצר הרע yeitzer hara is out to to seduce the right
you know, is being sent to seduce the good guys more than
the bad guys. And therefore it focuses more on ישראל Yisrael and
focuses more on the תלמידי חכמים Talmidei Chachamim and so on. But
that's a very different approach than the sort of psychological and internalized
approach. Yes.
That passage from יואל Yoel is in many נוסחאות nuschaot part of
the הפטרה haftarah for שבת שובה. Shabbat Shuva. Right. So yeah, exactly.
It's about that issue about dealing with our, right, exactly. All right.
אמר רב יצחק, Amar Rav Yitzchak, יצרו של אדם. Yitzro shel adam.
So now and now talking about the external and internal, notice about
also the how it has now become a possessive. So it started
with the יצר הרע Yetzer Hara, as one entity that has focuses
on ישראל Yisrael to destroy the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Now it
goes from being a single entity to being a
possessive. Your יצר הרע, yetzer hara, right? It's now personalized, so you
really see that shift. יצרו של אדם, yitzro shel adam, the יצר,
yeitzer, your יצר, yeitzer right? So כל הגדול מחבירו יצרו, kol hagadol
mechavero yitzro, his יצר yeitzer is greater. So here's the same point.
אמר רב יצחק, Amar Rav Yitzchak, יצרו של אדם, yitzro shel adam,
the יצר yeitzer of a person, so the one that's yours in
particular, מתגבר עליו בכל יום, mitgaber alav bechol yom, that every day
is getting stronger over you. שנאמר, as it says, רק
רע כל היום, rak ra kol hayom, it's only evil the whole
day. So every day it's like it doesn't lose any momentum. Okay,
and the or the evil increases every day. אמר ריש לקיש, Amar
Reish Lakish, יצרו של אדם, yitzro shel adam, again notice how we've
switched from יצר הרע yetzer hara, to יצרו של אדם yitzro shel
adam to make it yours, so talking very much internalized. The יצר
of a person מתגבר עליו בכל יום ומבקש להמיתו. mitgaber alav bechol
yom umevakesh lahamito. Not only is it getting stronger every day, it's
trying to get it's trying to kill you, to bring you into
the way of death. שנאמר, probably religious death, spiritual death. צופה רשע
לצדיק ומבקש להמיתו, Tzofeh rasha latzaddik umevakesh lahamito, the wicked one looks
out looks for the for the righteous and tries to kill him.
ואלמלא הקדוש ברוך הוא שעוזר לו, ve'ilmalei hakadosh baruch hu she'ozer lo,
if God were not there to help you, so אינו יכול לו,
eino yachol lo, you would not have the strength on your own
to withstand it. שנאמר, as it says, השם לא יעזבנו בידו ולא
ירשיענו בהישפטו, Hashem lo ya'azvennu veyado velo yarshiennu behishafeto, God will not
abandon you into his hands so will not let you become evil
through his judgment, like through the this evil person's or the יצר
הרע's, yetzer hara, you know, attempts. תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, Tana devei
Rabbi Yishmael, תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, Tana devei Rabbi Yishmael, אם פגע
בך מנוול זה, im paga becha menuval zeh, if this disgusting one
seizes upon you, so משכהו לבית המדרש, mashcheihu leveit hamidrash, shlep him
into the בית מדרש. beit midrash. So your יצר הרע has accosted
you, you drag him in with you to the בית מדרש. beit
midrash. You make him your חברותא, chavrusa, means learn תורה. Torah. That
will help you if you're if you're seized by a desire, just
open up a ספר, sefer, learn תורה. Torah. שאם אבן הוא נימוח,
She'im even hu nimoach, and if it was as hard as a
rock, it'll melt through the
words of תורה. Torah, ואם ברזל הוא מתפוצץ, Ve'im barzel hu mitpotzetz,
it'll shatter. אם אבן הוא נימוח,
Im
even
hu nimoach, if it's like a rock, it'll melt by words of
תורה, Torah דכתיב, dechtiv, הוי כל צמא לכו למים, hoy kol tzamei
lechu lamayim, come all thirsty to the water. So
so תורה's Torah like water. דכתיב, Dechtiv, and it says by water,
אבנים שחקו מים, avanim shachaku mayim, stones were worn away by water.
So
the
water will wear it away. ואם ברזל הוא מתפוצץ, Ve'im barzel hu
mitpotzetz, if it's like iron, it'll shatter.
דכתיב, Dechtiv, as it says, הלא כה
דברי כאש נאם השם וכפטיש
יפוצץ סלע,
halo cho
devari ka'esh neum Hashem uchefatish
yefotzetz sela, so are my words like fire, says God, like a
anvil, like a hammer breaks a rock. Now there's a
little bit of a problem here that רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot
both pick up on, which is that the the hammer is breaking
the rock. It's not we said, you know, if it's iron, it'll
shatter. But in the image, it's not the iron that's
shattering, it's the rock that's shattering. Right, you see
the problem here? Right? So yes, everybody sees this problem? So anyway,
so רש"י Rashi says that it's not by the end of the
פסוק pasuk, of breaking the rock, it's that God's
words are like fire. So what does fire do to iron? It
melts
it, it makes it spark. So that's
what רש"י says is the
image, not the breaking
of
the rock. תוספות Tosafot suggests reading the פסוק, pasuk. וכפטיש uchefatish and
a hammer יפוצץ סלע yefotzetz sela rock will break it. But that's
a pretty bad read of the פסוק. pasuk Anyway, but so the
image is a little bit of a challenge. Anyway, bring it into
the בית המדרש beit hamidrash and the תורה will will be able
to make it dissolve. אמר רבי שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי יונתן,
Amar Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yonatan, יצר הרע מסיתו לאדם
בעולם הזה, yeitzer hara mesito la'adam ba'olam hazeh, יצר הרע seduces
man in this world, ומעיד עליו
לעולם הבא, ume'id alav le'olam haba, and then will come and be
the enemy to, you know, the witness to to testify against you
in the world to come. Do do it, do it, do this
sin, do this sin, and then it becomes it seems like it's
your friend and then when it comes to sign time, it's going
to turn around on you, it'll be a and testify against you.
שנאמר, the verse says, מפנק מנוער עבדו, mefanek mino'ar avdo, literally this
means one who indulges from youth his slave, ואחריתו יהיה מנון, ve'acharito
yihyeh
manon, will be a מנון. manon. Now,
so מפנק מנוער עבדו mefanek mino'ar avdo means the somehow the יצר
הרע is called your slave. רש"י says because ultimately it is under
your control, but it has
been seducing you and allowing you to indulge yourself since
you've been a young, and
the end it will
be a מנון. manon. Now what's a מנון? manon? שכן באטב"ח של
רבי חייא, Sheken be'atbach shel Rabbi Chiya, because in the אטב"ח atbach
of רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya, קורין לסהדא מנון, korin lesahada manon, you
call a witness מנון, manon, מנון. manon. What does this mean? So
this word, by the way, מנון, manon, and this is a פסוק
pasuk in איוב, Iyov, right? It's one of those words that like
who knows what it means? You get in your English meaning of
Hebrew uncertain. So it's interesting that what חז"ל Chazal are trying to
do here is use a like a a type of a letter
substitution. What? Oh משלי, Mishlei, I'm sorry, some of the other ones
were from משלי. Mishlei. ו ז ח ט. Vav Zayin Chet Tet.
Hold on. Now I got confused. One minute. Oh right, 'cause the
ה, Heh, alright, 'cause the ה Heh is the five. ו ז
ח ט, Vav Zayin Chet Tet, okay? So those are one through
nine, okay? And then you have י כ ל מ נ ס
ע פ צ, Yud Kaf Lamed Mem Nun Samech Ayin Peh Tzadi,
so that's ten through ninety, right? Right, everyone knows the number substitution
here, right? ק ר ש ת. Kuf Reish Shin Tav. Okay, so
basically, do I have that right? Yeah. Okay. No, ק צדי ק
ר ש ת. Kuf Tzadi Kuf Reish Shin Tav. Oh, yeah, 'cause
רש״י Rashi does with... whatever. ק ר ש ת. Kuf Reish Shin
Tav. Oh, oh, oh, 'cause then what you do is, then you
do, so you have the last ones here and then you do
the סופית. Sofit. So, okay, so you have ס סופית, Samech Sofit,
מ סופית... Mem Sofit... am I getting that wrong? I'm sorry, מ
סופית, Mem Sofit, נ סופית, Nun Sofit, excuse me. מ סופית, Mem
Sofit, נ סופית, Nun Sofit, פ סופית, Peh Sofit, and צ סופית.
Tzadi Sofit. Okay, whatever. Okay, so anyway, fine. Anyway you see what
you do, that took way too long. You see what you do
is you sort of fold over the ones, the tens, and these
are the hundreds and these are the סופית Sofit letters. And then
you do a letter substitution, okay? So when you have,
when you have an extra letter, when you have one letter you
substitute it. So anyway if you do מנון, Manon, so how does
מנון Manon work? So the מ Mem here substitutes with a ס,
Samech, the נ, Nun, you know, these are left together so the
נ Nun substitutes with a ה, Heh, the ו Vav substitutes with
a ד, Dalet, and the נ Nun substitutes with a ה. Heh.
So מנון Manon becomes סהדה Sahada which is witness.
That took too long.
Okay, anyway, moving on.
Okay, so he'll be a witness for you in the end.
Okay. רב הונא רמי כתיב, Rav Huna Rami Ksiv, רב הונא Rav
Huna shows a contradiction. One verse says: כי רוח זנונים התעה, Ki
Ruach Znunim Hit'ah, because
a licentious spirit has led them astray. וכתיב: Uch'siv: בקרבם, Bekirbam, in
their midst. So is it external, this is the question, or is
it internal? So בתחילה התאם, Bitchila hit'am, initially
it just led them off the דרך, derech, but it wasn't a
completely internalized or it wasn't an occasional thing.
אבל בסוף בקרבם, Aval besof bekirbam, and then in the end it
became inside them in their very midst and it became internalized and
it became a regular, you know, a regular leading astray, a regular
sinning.
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, בתחילה קראו הולך, Bitchila karao holech, it's also
like the גמרא before, although it's external internal, the גמרא before about
the spiderweb and the thick cords, you know, about how it begins
one way and it gets then more and more your practice. אמר
רבא, Amar Rava, says רבא, Rava, בתחילה קראו הולך, Bitchila karao holech,
originally it was called a passerby, the יצר הרע, ובסוף קראו אורח,
Ubesof karao oreach, then it became a guest, spent a little time
by you, it wasn't just an
occasional temptation, it became a guest, it was a more regular visitor,
ובסוף קראו איש, Ubesof karao ish, and then it became like the
בעל הבית, Ba'al Habayit, it became the owner of the house. שנאמר,
as we see by דוד, it says this is the משל mashal
given to him
about the sin of בת שבע Batsheva by גד. Gad. ויבא הולך
לאיש העשיר, Vayavo holech le'ish he'ashir, remember this story about the two
men, the one that had all these sheep and the one that
had just one little sheep and then a visitor came to the
rich man and he didn't want to use any one of his
own sheep. of his sheep so he stole the sheep from the
poor man who only had one. So ויבוא הלך לאיש העשיר, Vayavo
helech l'ish he'ashir, so a passerby came to the wealthy man, ויחמול
לקחת מצונו ומבקרו, vayachmol lakachas mitzono umivkaro, the wealthy man didn't want
to take from his flock, לעשות לאורח, la'asos l'oreach, to do, to
make a meal for the guest. וכתיב ויקח את כבשת האיש הרש,
Uchsiv vayikach es kivsas ha'ish harash, so he took the sheep of
the poor man, ויעשה לאיש הבא אליו, vaya'aseh la'ish haba elav, and
he made for the man who came to him. So the man
who came to him started as a passerby, became an אורח, oreach,
and then became an איש. ish. Now who's who in this משל?
mashal? Well, the sheep are the wives of דוד, and the one
sheep is בת שבע, Bas Sheva, the wife of אוריה. Uriya. So
those are the men and those are the sheep. Who's the passerby?
So who's the passerby that needs to be fed? So the passerby
that needs to be fed is דוד's יצר הרע, right? So your
sexual desire needed to be fed. You didn't want to satisfy it
with your own wives, you had to take the wife of this
one poor man. So this desire, right, starts off as a passerby,
becomes a guest, and winds up being the man. אמר רבי יוחנן,
Amar Rabi Yochanan, אבר קטן, eiver katan, and now we're really turning
explicitly to a discussion of sexual desire. There's one little member, organ,
יש לו לאדם, yeish lo l'adam, that a man has. מרעיבו שבע,
mar'ivo saveia, if he makes it go hungry, he'll be satisfied. ומשביעו
רעב, umasbi'o ra'eiv, and if he satisfies it, he'll always be hungry.
So the more you give into the desire, the more it whets
the desire. שנאמר, as it says,
כמרעיתם וישבעו, kemar'isam vayisba'u, as they made it hungry, so they were
satisfied. Or that's how it's being read, as opposed to they grazed,
they were satisfied anyway. אמר רב חנא, Amar Rav Chana, so basically,
a certain degree of abstinence is healthy for controlling your sexual desire.
אמר רבי יוחנן בר אבא אמר בי רב, Amar Rabi Yochanan bar
Abba amrei bei Rav, ארבעה מתחרט עליהם הקדוש ברוך הוא שבראם, arba'ah
mischarat aleihem Hakadosh Baruch Hu shebera'am, four entities God, you know, regrets
having created. Not literally, but you know, sort of they create a
lot of evil in the world, they're necessary but they do a
lot of evil. ואלו הן, v'eilu hein, these are they: גלות, galus,
כשדים, Kasdim, וישמעאלים, v'Yishma'eilim, ויצר
הרע. v'yetzer hara. וואו. Wow. גלות דכתיב, Galus dichsiv, ועתה מה לי
פה נאם ה', v'atah mah li foh ne'um Hashem, what am I
doing here says God, כי לוקח עמי חנם, ki lukach ami chinam,
my nation have been taken for naught. So there was like, no
purpose to it. It shouldn't have happened, there shouldn't have been גלות
galus in the world. כשדים דכתיב, Kasdim dichsiv, הן ארץ כשדים זה
העם לא היה, hein eretz Kasdim zeh ha'am lo hayah, this is
the nation that hasn't been, meaning should never have been. I'm not
exactly what relevance that has. ישמעאלים דכתיב, Yishma'eilim dichsiv, ישליו אהלים לשודדים,
yishlayu ohalim l'shodedim,
will be tranquil, the tents will be tranquil for the robbers,
not robbers, whatever, anyway, something, for those, for those that, what's the
word? I can't think of the right word. Anyway, ובטחות למרגיזי אל,
uvtuchos l'margizei Eil,
and will have, you know, protection for those that anger God, לאשר
הביא אלוה בידו la'asher heivi Eloah beyado that God has brought through
His own hand. So meaning that God's created them, but there's a
sense of regret, like shouldn't have created them because of this sense
that they'll be שודדים, shodedim, you know, again, I can't come up
with the right word. What does it have there for שודד? shoded?
Provokers? No. Highway robbers? Highway robbers. All right. Robbers.
Okay.
Robbers. All right. Okay. Robbers. And finally, the point of this is
יצר הרע דכתיב, yetzer hara dichsiv, ויצר הרע, v'yetzer hara, as it
says, ואשר הרעתי, va'asher hareios, that I have done evil. So meaning,
and this is being read in the context of the earlier verse
which is that talks about God bringing those that have been led
astray. The things that, you know, that I have done evil, like
it was evil that I had created the reason for them to
be led astray, or the evil thing that I had created, the
יצר הרע, which shows a regret about it. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar
Rabi Yochanan, אלמלא שלש מקראות הללו, ilmalei shalosh mikra'os halalu, were it
not for the following three verses, נתמוטטו רגליהם של שונאיהם של ישראל,
nismotetu ragleihem shel soneihem shel Yisrael, the legs of the haters of
Israel would be, would you know, would fall aside, which means that
the Jewish people would not have what, again, it's a euphemistic way
of referring to the Jewish people, would not have what to withstand.
Meaning these פסוקים pesukim give us a little bit of a defense
of how we have sinned so much. So why? חד דכתיב, Chad
dichsiv, ואשר הרעתי, va'asher hareios, God takes responsibility for creating the יצר
הרע, so it's not all our fault. וחד דכתיב, V'chad dichsiv, הנה
כחומר ביד היוצר כן אתם בידי נאם ה', hineh kachomer beyad hayotzer
kein atem beyadi ne'um Hashem, like plaster, like, you know, clay in
the hand of the potter, which means that God could give us
the strength to be better. You know, so it's sort of God
has created us this way. ואידך והסרתי את לב האבן מבשרכם ונתתי
לכם לב בשר. V'idach vahasiri es lev ha'even mibesarcham venasasi lachem lev
basar. Again, God has put this heart of stone in our hearts
and God could give us a heart of flesh. So in a
way, God created us this way. So it's a little bit, you
know, again, doesn't mean it's, you know, we're not responsible for our
actions, but also we work, you know, we're human beings and we
were created with some of these frailties. Okay, רב פפא אמר. Rav
Pappa amar. God has put this heart of stone in our hearts
and God could give us a heart of flesh, so in a
way, God created us this way, so it's a little bit, again,
doesn't mean we're not responsible for our actions, but also we work,
we're human beings and we were created with some of these frailties.
Okay, רב פפא אמר אף מהאי נמי, Rav Papa amar af mei-hai
nami, even from the following verse, ואת רוחי אתן בקרבכם, ve-es ruchi
eten bekirbechem, I will give my spirit in you, which again means
that God could give us a stronger spirit. Let's just do a
little bit more. ויראני ה' ארבעה חרשים, Vayar'eni Hashem arba'ah charashim, a
vision and God showed me the four plowmen, or what were the
four plowmen? מאי ניהו ארבעה חרשים, Mai nihu arba'ah charashim, or the
four
craftsmen? So אמר רב חנא בר ביזנא אמר רבי שמעון חסידא, Amar
Rav Chana bar Bizna amar Rabbi Shimon Chasida, משיח בן דוד, here
are the four craftsmen: משיח בן דוד, ומשיח בן יוסף, u-Mashiach ben
Yosef, ואליהו, ve-Eliyahu, וכהן צדק. ve-Kohen Tzedek. So why are they craftsmen?
So Rashi says Mashiach ben David and Mashiach ben Yosef will bring
about the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, so they'll fashion the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash. Eliyahu made the altar at הר כרמל Har Carmel where
he fought with the נביאי הבעל, nevi'ei ha-Ba'al, and כהן צדק Kohen
Tzedek is, he reads it as מלכי צדק Malki-Tzedek who was a
son of Noach who helped build the תיבה. tevah. All right. So
fine. מתיב רב ששת, Masiv Rav Sheshet, אי הכי היינו דכתיב, i
hachi hainu de-chtiv, if such good guys, what's meant by the next
verse where God says ויאמר אלי אלה הקרנות אשר זרו את יהודה,
Vayomer elai eleh ha-kranot asher zeru es Yehudah, these are the horns
that scattered Yehuda? הני לשובא אתו? Hani le-shuva asu? Or some say
יסובו מיהודה? yasuvu mi-Yehudah? These these these are the ones that scattered
Yehuda? Is that what—and these are good guys.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, no, שפיל לסיפא דקרא, shafil le-seifa di-kra, look
at the end of the verse. ויבאו אלה להחריד אותם לידות את
קרנות הגוים הנושאים קרן אל ארץ יהודה לזרותה. Vayavo'u eleh le-hacharid osam
lidot es karnot ha-goyim ha-nosim keren el eretz Yehudah le-zarosah. He says,
no, the end of the verse says these, not these guys, not
the four חרשים, charashim, these others, these were the horns that scattered
Yehuda and these, these, these four חרשים charashim are going to come
to tremble them and to destroy these horns that carried away the
land of Yehuda and that attacked Yehuda. You have to look inside,
but basically it says here are the four חרשים, charashim, these are
those, the horns that scattered Yehuda and they will come to destroy
those horns. So the "these" of the horns is not referring to
the four חרשים, charashim, all right?
So he said to him, בהא חנא באגדתא לא מציתי, Be-ha Chana
be-Agadeta la matzisai, I should have known better than to compete with
Chana by אגדתא, Agadeta, which is pretty funny because actually it's פשט
pshat of the פסוקים, psukim, but okay, whatever. One last thing. והיה
זה שלום אשור כי יבא בארצנו, Ve-hayah zeh shalom Ashur ki yavo
be-artzeinu, this will be the peace of Ashur when if Ashur comes
against our land, וכי ידרוך בארמנותינו, ve-ki yidroch be-armonoseinu,
and trample on our castle, meaning to destroy the בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash, והקימונו עליו שבעה רועים ושמונה נסיכי אדם. va-hakimonu alav shiv'ah ro'im
u-shmonah nesichei adam. What will we do is that there will be
seven shepherds and eight like leaders of people, and the end of
the פסוק is, and they'll take over the land of Ashur. They're
trying to attack us, we'll take over their land with these seven
shepherds and eight leaders. מני ניהו שבעה רועים, Mani nihu shiv'ah ro'im,
who are the seven shepherds? דוד באמצע, David ba-emtza, first David, אדם
שת ומתושלח מימינו, Adam Shes u-Mesushalach mi-yimino, אברהם יעקב ומשה בשמאלו. Avraham
Yaakov u-Moshe bi-smolo. Okay, now of course they're all shepherds in the
sense that they were leaders. Of course the מהרש"א Maharsha points out
that most of them were actually literally shepherds as well, which is
interesting. Okay, where exactly is Yitzchak is not clear. Fine. ומני ניהו
שמונה נסיכי אדם, U-mani nihu shmonah nesichei adam, who are the eight
leaders of people? ישי ושאול ושמואל עמוס וצפניה צדקיה ומשיח ואליהו. Yishai
ve-Shaul u-Shmuel Amos ve-Tzefaniah Tzidkiyahu u-Mashiach ve-Eliyahu. And for homework you can
figure out what those eight have anything to do with one another,
I don't know. Okay.
These are all anti-Christian,
anti-apostle אגדתא. Agadeta.
Yeah, I was sort of guessing that, but you'd have to
look in the apostle for the justification, but it's also
clear from what he was saying. Are you coming over to our
house for ראש השנה? Rosh Hashanah? No I'm not.
Hello?
Yeah, yeah we're just leaving the דף. daf.